[Music]
so what do you say a SPECT search
meditation that I think probably most
people think about what they think
mother think meditation they'll be
thinking about so let's say focusing on
something yeah it's probably something
every we all done yeah in the beginning
yeah when you start practicing it I know
I did yeah that's the first thing you
come across the idea of meditation he's
the ideal
concentration in terms of focusing
focusing focusing Penix expecting the
results that have come automatically out
of you
just doing this method of focusing yeah
so what kind of folks in were you so I
guess first of all the idea was focusing
focusing your attention on this sort of
triangle here around your nose that
you're where breathing is happening so
you're basically just sort of focusing
on the process breathing and doing it as
a kind of observing air passing over
this area and then it was like and then
the idea was then all the smaller and
smaller you get that that area becomes
smaller as once more until until you've
focusing on focusing on just a pinpoint
Hey yeah and what were you thinking like
while you were doing the focusing
practice that I should be doing what am i doing
that I should be doing what am i doing
well no no when you would do the folks
who practice yeah I was there were your
thoughts in terms of what were you
thinking that you were focusing on okay
well that was the thing I was failing
right in the time wondering about that
what it was that was supposed to be
focusing on and was what I was doing and
where they're always doing it right but
that was all kind of superfluous to the
meditation sure but the meditation was
okay what are you focusing on here so
the idea I guess was what that was being
encouraged was a kind of I would say
like an objective sideways view on sure
on the thin air that happens to be patio
this area here house me breathing but if
you can perceive things yes there is out
there outside of your experience because
it doesn't prevent that person it
doesn't pertain to you to experience the
exception yeah that's the main that's
the fundamental problem with any
focusing practice whatever the technique
might be if it's a technique of
observation and focusing and sort of
preying upon moments as the suit that
was sort of described it the the problem
with that is you assume this external
world independent of your perception yet
the only way you can relate to it is to
perceive it as in the experience it but
you assume through experiencing it that
it's outside of your experience and you
can be objective about it but how can
you even conceive the idea of outside of
my experience unless you're thinking it
experientially so to speak so you're
contradicting one both fronts yeah and
that's the sole problem focusing on this
on account of that that's whatever
that's just what mine does mine picks
the dumbest to look at that's that's
just how it works are you assuming that
those things stand for that which they
cannot stand for such as an external
world independent of me that is
subjected to this scientific laws of
impermanence thus the buddha and the
science are saying the same thing all
these were views that you here today are
completely misguided because they're
rooted in this author assumption of
external to me yeah
the only work in Norwich breeze
experiencing it by myself but is it
you're you're focusing on something
objective like there's this objective
side of lieth air that's how sure to be
going through this student subjective
nose on the front of my face
yeah but also this kind of you have to
sort of stand back and look at it from a
position of objectivity so your which is
very subjective
exactly how could even out of it doesn't
become purely objective because it's
inconceivable yeah that means like
stepping outside of the aggregates and
being there will be the objective matter
yeah that's inconceivable he just stops
appropriate in his subjectivity that's
all you got and still has like
individuality in terms of character
habits and all these things didn't know
lose it agree the worst delusion of
course and yet people find subjectivity
to be the problem and it is a problem
but then instead of understanding truly
what what is the problematic aspect of
subjectivity and then abandoning that
they think you can simply replace
subjectivity by emulating this
assumption of objectivity the only cop
isn't that kind of idea trying to get
rid of the basically there's always a
point of view yeah of course it's always
a question I cannot have I can't have an
experience without a point of view
whereas whereas many attitudes to
meditation that kind of trying to engage
my negate that trying to be a gather yet
they're trying to take third-person
perspective or like a god side you on
sure so we can do the same we will be
there before
let's take focusing now so focus on your
body touching the chair like right now
what are the characteristics of that how
would you describe it
well you asked me to focus on my body
get on the chair and I just sort of
looked into something that was already
there it's already kind of given this
sense of Shh yeah I can feel something
everybody some picking
it's totally inseparable from the body
mm-hmm it's not like yeah like the chair
touching my body my body touching the
chair it's just this kind of pressure
that or something I don't know that's a
touch base it's the only way should we
go ahead with it so if you're focusing
now I'm focusing as well you realize you
can only focus on something it's already
been given but now you have a choice
so yeah you focus on it as in you bring
your attention to it but now you have a
choice I have a choice you have
everybody has a choice and that choice
is I can now continue to just keep
repeating this focusing mechanically oh
I can try understand the nature of that
thing that's necessary for my focus and
you could see those those two are
mutually exclusive directions if I keep
open and touching the chair I'm touching
the chair I'm touching the chair means
you actively avoid in the direction of
okay you're touching the chair now let
it be there so you get to understand the
necessary basis for your attending that
in the first place which is that which
is all the other kind of diseases you
discussed in other videos okay so you
can only really focus on something
attend to something if it was given as a
possibility and by that I mean if it's
given beforehand it's already there thus
you were able to turn to it and at the
mind it's that peripheral aspect of oh
it's already there without me being
without directly
attending it so it's already there as a
possibility means it's already there on its own
means it's already there on its own
which means even my ownership is
secondary to that basis of possibilities
that the present himself as possibly
mine and you can get to understand it
and then you realize okay so that's all
you need to do stop regarding it as mind
and you can forget all the focusing you
want now you fulfill the purpose of your
folks but if your purpose is just to
focus for the sake of focusing means
you're actively then avoiding
understanding thing so so focusing so
people are like going in a particular
direct you said in mutually exclusive
direction so focusing in on this
mechanical particular thing well this
one particular thing and then and then
later though the next particular thing
yes sort of the same you're focusing as
a rule of thumb follows the the idea of
the expense of everything else and
that's why it's a problem because
because the founding he always rooted in
the totality of your experience exactly
in understanding the context of your
particular and that's why the whole
point is like yeah any form of focusing
is already singling out particular other
wisdom within that particular you can go
even further so you choosing to attend
your body position seated on the chair
it's a particular thing you focused on
and that's more than sufficient now you
want to understand the nature of that
thing that you focused on that is still
there cuz you brought your attention to
it and you don't need to keep holding on
to it because if I asked you are you
still touching the chair yes of course
you wouldn't hold on I need to figure it
out recall the memory now if the
knowledge is still there because you
attended it you clarified it but simply
by focusing on it but instead of that
then people who follow the rule of
focusing for the sake of focusing will
then focus on the chair then focus of
the more specific notions of your body
on the chair and focus on even more to
do so focus when you focus on using
folks in written form that's generally
the idea
that's how you arrived with some sort of
knowledge you realize but that's why I
ask you what do you think that you're
focusing on what can you focus on you
can only focus on a possibility that was
presented itself as being able to focus
which means when you start practicing
this focusing upon focusing and you
actually develop a belief that you are
focusing on the actual Rupa on the
actual matter on the actual objectivity
by linearity all you can focuses on your
thoughts in other words your thoughts
give you the focus that you can focus on
yeah so when you are thinking about the
objective matter you're thinking about a
foot that is fully misconceived the
nature of matter and presented itself as
death which is the matter and that's
like the essence of Mullaperiyar so tell
obviously taking your very extreme sense
but the point is even does matter how
far you committed in your focusing
practice how specifically how
particularly you're staring at things
all you can do is focus and inner ad and
there isn't Dhamma as such Dhamma has a
counterpart of your mind but it's not oh
I must stop doing that no all I have to
stop doing is stuff misconceiving that
my thoughts can stand for that objective
world which I keep sort of fueling the
assumption of it through this practice
of focusing because I am thinking I'm
getting closer to the pure materiality
or something they will then free me from
any subjectivity and basically the first
teaching is no just it's about
understanding except that's the thing
it's all about something else so what
you're saying is that focusing is about
getting deeper into the objects but
that's for what did well because that's
what I already say so some people and
they make a very they'll think they
think they will they'll respond and say
well I don't know but I get awesome
benefit from my meditation practice
which is focusing on small things yeah
things more particular I noticed the
more I do it the more refined and the
more subtle the more particular things
things I've never noticed before I start
to notice and
that means awareness right so what is
the nature of things found in the
particular exemplification on that they
don't see them in I don't exactly know
that's one say yeah which means they're
not interested in the Dhamma
no because the definition of the Dharma
means the things so the definition of
Domino is in the direction of the
general direction of opposite of the
direction of your particular focus so
what is it that keeps people doing this
why do people wonder so many people keep
going another right it's deeply to view
that you get rid of your uh tabata by
canceling it you get you overcome
subjectivity by denying it
there's no it's actually quite pleasant
oh yeah no that's not a more immediate
level I'm talking about to me but the
point when you mention like when you're
getting deeper into things that's
usually the belief but you're not
getting you can't get it you always
being on the surface that's all that
perception will always remain perceiving
the perception perception cannot really
bring you into the meta because that
would mean that you can access a looper
which the Buddha says is inaccessible it
can only find a footing in your
experience through you providing a basis
of misconceiving so you feels like feels
like anybody better do you always remain
yeah that's what I mean this matter how
far you got focused if you realize all
the focusing is on the Damas another
thing yeah so it doesn't matter if it's
this particular level this particular
level the nature it means completely the
same and if you are ignorant of that
means yeah you're pursued to focusing
his endless before which means I must be
learning things well that's and if you
would like
I remember for myself you stand of feels
like it feels like a novelty feels like
that or not like you're so focused on
particular movements basically kind of
exercising this this sort of contrived
sense of control but you can only
sustain that so far but initially it
creates this sense of novelty whereby
about experiencing things differently
yeah but again a new way new things are
happening new things all these as matter
where can difference happen
can happen to the level of particular it
also you can convince yourself that
you'll be more aware because you because
let's not jump into every possible angle
people can take let's just clarify the
pleasure we started on so the point is
if it comes down to again think about
yourself now focusing why would you why
would you carry on focusing as you send
this up because it it feels good it
feels peaceful it feels like less
cluttered and so on so bringing
attention to things feels let's close it
feels more directional that's fine but
why would they then justified you
constantly being attention brilliantly
should bring it there to bring attention
means you still don't understand where
that piece comes from and let's see the
other talk that s who explains like the
similar of the anchor throwing down the
anchor you throw the anchor and then you
let the boat sort of float around
because it's anchored so you know it
can't go too far you allow it to move
around the idea of focusing it's like
throw the anchor pull the anchor throw
the anchor throw the anchor throw the
anchor throw the anchor that's it
I'm focusing I'm focusing a focus
because the idea of floating about it's
too overwhelming so the whole point of
doing the folksy practice would be you
just want pleasure what you just want to
avoid any liability to suffering to the
trunk up to discomfortable feelings
uncomfortable feelings that's it so it
becomes a management to your liability
to suffer it oh if I focus hard enough
basically I won't think about things
that bother me yeah it's sort of
basically putting your head under yeah
and that's what I was saying the other
talkity the idea of concentration for
most people it's like you focus so hard
on one point where you forget everything
else and that's why exactly absolutely
if you're absorbed in something that
means you're basically not aware of
anything else but one pointedness is we
described before it's the point that
includes everything else regardless of
the content and that's exactly we
describe so you focused on your
experience as a whole my my experience
I'm focusing on being seated on the
okay you brought your attention to it
now that's the container for your
context let's see what comes up with it
oh so while I'm seated in the chair
we're talking about these various ideas
do the wrong didn't loot any wrong
assumptions policy to the chair wall up
see to the chair I have these feelings
arising while I'm sitting the chair and
I have these so other thoughts arising
ones here the trip but if you're doing
the folksy practice you'll be doing all
these things they're not happening but
I'm sitting in the chair I'm sitting on
touching touching leaning leaning
touching touching leaning thinking
thinking often you're not even did you
know you are but now you forgot that
because you think the whole purpose is
just to be fully absorbed in focusing
right in front of it and how can you
then be fully absorbed in what's in
front of you without doing that at the
expense of the nature of that thing it
expensive everything else that it's not
in front of you and that's that's right
it's inherently wrong you can't do it
right he says you not have the right
outcome canceling out the context
exactly about content yeah I'm just
interested delighting in the next thing
and that's another suit that the people
you know probably many people read but
it would not necessarily see a
connection with this we talked about is
that that one way says all this some of
the ground is I say we are meditators we
meditate and but what they do it's like
I look like an owl train the pollak
waiting for a fish or a jackal waiting
here exactly so imagine just don't take
my word for it imagine if you were a
hunter so there's a little hole and you
were waiting for I don't know a rabbit I
had to come out you want to catch it
what would you be doing
you'd be focusing you be focusing any
expense of everything yes because that's
how important this is to you know catch
it and when the Buddha described and
when he said all these people call
themselves meditators and all they do
they are like a jackal
to catch a prey they call the resulting
yeah so he basically trying to catch
trying to focus and catch an attending
grad with a moment whatever record and
he said whoever does that does so rooted
in sensuality they meditate with
sensuality cuz you made it in with that
laho this is on the basis of my senses
sense of touch sense of usually sense of
touch people tend to became divisional
whatever else audible the point is
you're catching the moment do you
believe that it has significance for you
profound significance you yourself kind
of gave it in a way with your wrong
views that if you catch the moment
rightly sufficient amount of time it
will purify everything that needs to be
purified without you needing to think
about it you want address it on an every
single basis so focus focus focus focus
focus got it I got the moment I had this
great experience my body felt so light
it was a disappeared into the day oh so
that must me mean that I've succeeded
somehow and that's usually like I have
experienced or now have to interpret it
which means I've no understanding of
experience now I had to fabricate it
because even if you have the lofty
unusual experience of your energy in
your body but not what's the nature it
means slightly less common experience of
this body here as opposed to more common
daily experience with this body here
either way there is this body here so
normally people would think you do the
meditation but then afterwards you'll
have this a profound experience and then
you have to make sure how to interpret
that sense of it but that actual making
sense out of it that's the meditation
yeah that's where you slug that's closer
I mean the best meditation will appraise
is a mutation of Jonah how do you love
Jonah by understanding with Johnny is so by
by understanding with Johnny is so by
not dwelling of the theme of Jonah as if
this is what Jonah is I keep thinking
about it very minute monk enters it by
not dwelling on the theme of Jonah
he doesn't develop it I suppose in it
but with the whole sort of you know
commentarial evolutionary take of Watson
austria's leached absorption leads to
jhana leads to whatnot
and I've consulted suit that doesn't
talk about jhanas at all and it could
then that looks about four foundations
of mindfulness so we practice
mindfulness of the breathing and
fulfills your awareness of the
peripheral fulfills your knowledge of
the background in regard to that which
you're focusing rather than rather than
have some sort of you mix the color
absorption of folks and that was there
was the meditation but I sell while I'm
sitting here I have such a such feeling
arising and enduring and I still feel
like that while I'm sitting here while
we're talking about these things you
know I don't need to try to catch up
with anything actually all you need to
do is stay that at the doorway which is
you determined through your initial
active focusing oh oh this is my
situation my situation is being sitting
on the chair in this room with two other
people and six dogs that's it
within that now everything that happens
will happen within it and you don't need
to chase it and countless simply look at
the game but usually the one demand sort
of surveys that the outskirts of the
city there's no any in-and-out way entry
or exit except one big gate and he
Desalle well if I stay the gate I'll know
well if I stay the gate I'll know
whoever's in there now who is out I
don't need to chase people individual in
we're trying to get them outside I just
need to stay here and the idea how do
you stay here while things are changing
so by focusing focusing focusing folks
means I'm at the gate I medicate I'm in
the gate
I'm in the game people coming in and out
for you are looking at the game no you
stay by understanding this so this is it
it's this is the present container this
is the entry and exit point I'll keep
that in mind that's it that's the money
keeping things in mind keeping things
together isn't it somehow composing
things so you compose your situation
through revealing it through attempt
attending to it so yeah it don't be
completely - and non attentive but doing
attention for sake retention means
actually ignoring the situation you
cannot do boo you cannot attend to that
which is better peripheral what you're
attending so I'm attending to this means
and other things that are there
simultaneously prize
it cannot be attended to and it's not a
point to attend all of them the point is
that what you attend recognize or attend
to that which is a natural container to
everything else basically the nature of
your experience involves the presence of
other things this periphery or dislike
other things that you want attending to
you right now yeah so if your person
your body for example I could allows you
to focus on something else
yeah it's equally there that can serve
as a footing for anchoring but like so
any any meditation that avoids this kind
of that avoids acknowledging the
periphery of whatever it is you're
attending to is meetcha it's not been
missing the whole nature they were
experience it's gonna be like a Jacko
trying opponent ignoring everything else
it's like a cat catching the fish and
ignoring everything else and the Buddha
mocked it he said with his shoulders
drooping head swinging basically
sleeping drooling powerful concentration
we're at it isn't it fully that's
generally that is that that is actually
the nature falling asleep when you fall
asleep yep everything excluded
everything you're lying on your bed and
you're thinking about whatever it is
you're thinking about but then at some
point you forget the background wait oh
I'm lying in my bed here sure and you've
done and you're absorbed in the
particular so that's why even in your
dreams if you end up in the dream something
if you end up in the dream something
that requires slightly hide the glue of
reflection you need any wake up yeah
this is how it works
oh you just remember where you are oh we
can't think down for you here yeah
that's for working so so basically the
common idea about what meditation is
is very similar to happens when you fall
asleep either way yeah yeah I think a
similar physical manifestations but
another another thing that they don't
often get tighter than this folks in
plastics track practice practice is the
idea of sensations yeah as if some sort
of a hybrid phenomenon it's kind of in
between perception and feelings so
beginning I was saying talk about
focusing on focusing on this but another
thing how I used to fear anything a lot
of people think it's yeah so focusing on
sensations in the body with the
rationale the baths sure sure feeling
but then with the Buddhist trying to
read he said well they are pleasant
unpleasant neutral so what difference
does it make if the sensation is in your
elbows or your shoulders or your nose
when all you need to look for is this
Pleasant a pleasant and neutral and if
you start looking at you'll see the
pleasantness unpleasantness in
neutrality is not localized in your
perception of spatial body cannot be
count so what they say
orderly feeling it's basically a mental
feeling in regard to the body when they
say mental mental feeling it's a mental
feeling in regard to the mind either way
feeling is Chetta Sica as the Buddha
said in the Sutra it's mental always
mental so you observing observing there
you go observing sensation your legs
means you're perceiving sense of touch
in your legs the dance somehow starts to
stand for the feeling vadhana so how can
you perceive retina how's it possible
I'm perceiving what I'm feeling but the
Buddha said feeling is that which feels
that it's felt and perceptions that
which perceives is deceived so how can
you then perceive what you feel the
sensations are of you
be described as like well I'm the
quality of perceptions they describe
this feelings if you look at feelings
they'll describe these perceptions yes
and you will maintain that ambiguity
that confusion that contradiction
because you don't clarify what it is
said that's it so when my people are
observing sensations exactly like you're
kind of standing back like I have
supposedly described as like a doctor
imagine you're a doctor looking down
that's all fine so that's the third
nobody realize the existence of
sensations or that which you refer to a
sensation is but if the confusion that
you imply with it as if that which
you're perceiving is your feeling that's
all I need to do is stop ignoring how
they work start ignoring or maintain the
imminence of how I'm actually feeling
and keep hoping for the right perception
that will reveal the nature of feeling
and everything else to me because you
assume that it can be perceived so you
can I have very sensations in my back
after a universe of these things you but
that's not how I feel those are things
that I perceive because the body's
spacial three-dimensional it has the
inside has the outsides and you know
touch receptors go both ways so you can
feel it turn all sort of perceptions
which are sensations but then you say
that that's what your feelings are
that's how you maintain the wrong view
because feelings are felt on the level
of the mind that's what I always start
with like what's your mood right now
that's where the feelings are yeah no
I'm feeling I'm feeling pleasure in my
hand no you have agreeable perceptions
in your hand to the resulting experience
of pleasure yeah that's it so it's all
you must stop paying attention to
sensation though it just oh stop must
stop misconceiving feelings we have
Association feelings in my body
exactly feelings being in a place yeah
feelings are placed in this body
so then you can measure the feeling by
the means of perceptions yeah it was
like it's surgery I had my hand oh and
they sort of put in the area they
numbered out so you don't feel anything
difference yeah the language is yeah so
you don't sense anything you're
insensitive pain but there were not many
lot and I could feel them putting on the
tendons yeah yeah which is not something
that's agreeable to me yeah so I'm gonna
feel that and I thought ah it's not dumb
enough cuz after the pain yeah yeah I
feel pain yeah but I'm sensing only the
putting of the tendon which is
disagreeable and so there would numb it
out here more and still the payment then
I realized oh it they've gone numb that
they cannot knock out no feeling that
but they can numb they can change the
sensations that's how people experience
experience pain in the limbs after the
loss a hole in racking I'm feeling in
regard that's the thing feeling is
always phantom from the point of your
perception feeling can ever enter the
domain of perception so you have feeling
perception and intention are impossible
to disjoin as the Buddha said so
whenever there is a perception there is
a simultaneously present enduring
feeling this is a grave of perception
but then some people will find it
pleasurable there are people who find
pain being a Concord discomfort extreme
piercing discomfort being inflicted on
the body they find pleasure in it there
are other people who have extreme amount
of comfort afflicted to the body and
they still find it painful
so my determine is basically the
threshold of what's gonna be painful or
not hence still you know the trained
body the body resistant to elements can
endure much more the mind developed in
Jonah's can endure the roughness of the
root of a tree horrible of fermented
urine for the medicine rough hand probes
will be like silk and basmati rice in
the king's palace that's how it will be
felt and that's why I would have said
you should practice John and develop
your mind in that sense Corrections
but if you think that you can actually
perceive your feelings whether you're
completely it's uncalled for but you end
up giving significance to your
perception that doesn't deserve it
should be there it's miss consuming it
so you don't need to deny sensations or
say sensations are wrong you just need
to understand them and you'll see if
you're either taking the misperceptions
that stand in for feelings or feelings
to send perceptions or both but once you
clarify them you won't do that anymore
so you can still use it as a designation
and a form of speech yeah but sensations
in my life I better change my posture
that's it disagreeable perceptions
agreeable perceptions but how you feel
is in its own domain and he can never
mix with any other domain and you aren't
gonna find invaded by focusing no
because what you can focus on is which
you can observe and you can't observe
feelings you can only feel them but if
your only means of any form of effort is
of the level of focusing focusing is
this whole domain of what's being felt
right there simultaneous ability is
invisible to knowledge however is a
blanket access to all of the domains
nature understanding the nature of
things that you're not directly focusing
on but the setting in as a necessary
basis means its base for it
understanding intention feeling and
perception feel better but yeah you can
use a base of perception to establish
and choreograph your mindfulness like
for example light now right here in oh
yeah if I ask you is there light or is
it dark which one is it now that's light
so whatever you do whatever we say
whatever you feel whatever you tell
where your body moves it's done within
the container of the light and still in
use and that's not a new you didn't
create this light use their a reason
they provide a basis for the whole
experience on a more particular level
and it's not something I can focus on I
can't see it exactly so you do anchoring
properly you do focusing properly it's
something you don't focus on anymore
like focusing means bringing attention
to it but doesn't mean keep attending
attending keep it that means you should
understand it now that you attended it
even so even perceptions aren't really
things that I'm attending attending to
you any of their lives for them that
exactly yeah so like that's what the
Buddha as you say those things but
within that I can I can discern various
perceptions they're always peripheral if you have a
they're always peripheral if you have a
view that you must attend in focus you
have a view that prioritizes the content
yeah off whatever you're focusing on
attending which means there has to be
done in the expense of the nature that's
what it would have said whatever
aggregate or perception so whatever
perception old-new past future far near
up down left right whatever particularly
the perception might be he knows
perception is there he doesn't oh this
is no perception is there because he has
to be in some way and so you stop being
concerned about what way perception is
there you know perception is there
whatever feeling us present future
fatherly it personally personal pleasant
unpleasant feeling is there so every
aggregates can be is present
particularly but if that's all you seen
you're ignorant of its nature misery no
not the Dhamma so that's right focusing
outlines the picture for you but
understanding is on the level of the
opposite of what you're attending
that's why Jani sir
man a saccade of the origin from the
origin so knowing the origin of this
very thing that I'm attending while this
origin of their attention is present
different sort of food
how could you attend the origin of your
attention you want to offend it even it
is much oh I will see my eye with the
same eye yeah that is inconceivable but
I will know that there is that because
of which I am able to see then I cannot
see but I can know that it's there as a
necessary basis namely the eye that's
properly exercised yoni so Melissa car
has only the suitors
yeah as most people would think yummy so
means attending carefully attending you
cannot dance it can bring on the level
of nature of things not on the level of
what you can make observe the step
because it is the origin of my attention
how can that same attention attend
itself in its origin impossible and the
only reason you would keep assuming that
this because you you don't clarify
sufficiently enough that it is
impossible because if you do your
efforts they would be trying to attend
to it like a sir could be a context well
yeah tell me what can you attend something in
tell me what can you attend something in
from nothingness
nobody needs to be there beforehand and
that context is the origin of this thing
in a sense that this thing couldn't be
what it is without this whole logic
on-site field Oh attend to your elbows
touching the chair how can you do that
if you wouldn't have elbows there is no
chair if you're not seated in a
particular position of a few requiring
requiring you being leaning on the chair
how can you attention you can't so the
only way you can attend it if it's
already bitten during and when you're
still you attend to any aspect it's not
you know begun yeah it's been going on I
understand that that's how you also
become unable to regard the most
volitional choice decision as mine
could you see fully encapsulated within
that which cannot be yours
well the option to choose choice as they
see he chooses that choice is always
being there yeah and then or you can
even look I'm still sitting here yeah
yeah some thought the choice to such a
still going on yeah and if you say no
but I have a choice to stand up and
change their situation yes and you can
only do that because there is a
possibility for you as in for the body
to be moved in an upright position so
you when you stand up you just exercise
another choice on top of the choice
between exercise
of you sitting so there's no matter
there is no such choice that can take
you outside of the given container of
your experience as a home from which you
can really impartial E or independently
or black as a master choose without any
basis for that choice it's always
secondary to it
so the choice the effects of your choice
the results of your action are within
your experiences are over there seconded
it to it so if I choose to stand up I've
changed my initially determined sort of
base for my mindfulness that I focused
on initially to just discern it but now
I can only change it because there is
another potential basis that this can be
replaced with hence the four body
postures because there's no fifth by the
way you're either gonna be standing
laying down and walking or sitting
that's it so you leave that's way less
when you start realizing it doesn't
matter how much I exercise my choice
within this it's going to be within some
limiting container fundamentally that
limiting container is the five
aggregates or the life in itself you
can't do anything unless you alive so I
missed it alive yes so that's your the
most general container because if that's
taken away which can be at any moment oh
I am NOT saying that my whole life
depends upon a muscle that beats inside
of my chest can I even conceive telling
it how to beat how fast no it's just
inaccessible to you inaccessible to the
wildest of your imagination yet you're
retired life sits on it lettuce and you
can't even imagine this thing how to
change what will happen to it and if
that goes none of this can remain so if
you keep that context in your mind
that's basically modernist art done
correctly everything is then put against
the backdrop of it's unknowable because
it's rooted in something that I cannot
even have in my imagination left alone
in practice that's whatever I do on top
of it is equally an honorable
me because if you are the owner you're
the master you're the controller you're
in charge of it how can you be in charge
of something you can't even imagine
you can't even know the ending
okay you know but you can know that it's
gonna end it's good but because he has
an originator from you is it already
falling upon SEC it's my own things
don't you hear you come inaccessible
that's the suffering that it's the
murderer waiting to stay well that's the
emergency that's a Nietzsche uncommon of your come
that's a Nietzsche uncommon of your come
on each a means impossible to own
impossible to be mine and what if it's
unknowable and yet here I am depending
on it and suffering if it's honorable it
is dukkha if I don't agree with you
occur then have this sense of myself I
don't own even that so if it's
unknowable and dukkha then my experience
is an utter you don't need to do an
after then
oh this is your permanence this is
suffering and this is the not self no
this is impermanence this is suffering
this experience is experienced as not
self so if you see your sense of self as
inseparably rooted in that which cannot
be your sense of self which is
unknowable inaccessible to you even in
your imagination then your sense of self
right here and then will be felt as not
my sense of self so after an anata means
to basically my self or not my self
and it doesn't mean there's no self
cause if there is no self what are you
designating by saying there is no self
it's like allowing that understanding
2000 long enough in the background yeah
it's a kind of color yeah an influence
because you will see that everything
that you're doing is bound up with
enough like even though you like
ignoring that you can order that then
takes you in the direction of all I am
doing this in a sense of I am controller
master of this but at any given point
you can reestablish the fundamental
context it if it random muscle that
pumps blood from your chest he that
stops no matter your projects feelings
hopes dreams memories traumas happiness
sadness can you may not for a second
look and ok so what do you do next
nothing clarify that same thing that's
what you do next just allow it to do you
make it clearer and clearer and clearer
and harder and harder to forget that
that's my heart running both howling
both I get with things simultaneously
present is the basis for those things
that it's inaccessible to me and when I
say base of us things I'm a basis for
your own life as well because your life
is another thing that's it and you
couldn't see how that this contemplation
meditation Samadhi would automatically
result in this passion
how can you access this passion to this
when you cannot possibly but lose the
sight of the context that it's
inherently inaccessible to you an
honorable not worth the effort
and that's what verse is like when the
monk rates is rightly he starts
developing these notions that oh this is
not worth engaging with this is not
worth delighting here I can still do it
but now the unworthy aspect of this is
way overwhelming and then you can't do
it in the only way you would the only
reason we're doing it is because you
will find any worthy of doing it
oppression of the gods
exactly passionate about it but not even
it become impossible passion is
worthless effort of investing passion is
uncle it becomes inconceivable without
the lighting or not it is what it is
that's not mine that's it and you don't
need to hire master what just don't lose
the sight of that peripheral context
doesn't matter what you're particularly
attending beautiful aspects ugly ass be
beautiful I spent ugly-ass bit Schneider
it's in the context of being all rooted
in something that I cannot even conceive
owning thus pleasure pain stops
bothering me and that the light is
naturally falls off excellent so you
have to kind of fight that Alliant you
just kind of yeah just need to make it
the context in face of it yeah that's it
but if all you're doing is focusing
what's in front of you means your mind
will be fully taken by pleasure
fully taking my pain because you're
resisting the pain because they're long
in flesh that will always be peripheral
which is you've chosen not to look yeah
the knowledge is on the level of
peripheral because you have to keep
keeping things that you know in your
mind means you have really understood it
if you keep reminding yourself because
if you forget the knowledge goes with it
which means that's not knowledge things
that you really understood you stopped
thinking about yeah and if they brought
up the understanding is they're like the
Buddha the simile that when a man asked
him I mean has the world do was to
prepare these answers beforehand
yeah people asking say well let me ask
in return Europe must the chariot maker
or whatever he was if I were to ask you
anything about the workings of the
chariots of parts would you need to
prepare the answer oh oh people wake me
up in the middle of the night
and asked me a question I'm given the
answer because I have understood how
sharing works old engineering did I
never fully understood so I don't need
to prepare anything when it's asked the
answers there from that understood
context and he said that is the
same that's how it doesn't fit very
answers where because you understood it
well if you again similar the same
chariot Monica if you haven't understood
how the chariot actually works but you
read about it then you okay so the
wheels the wheels the wheels don't give
a
the CT how does we think about
executives you stop thinking about it
come o how does he work how does he
working it means you haven't understood
it and it's not a big surprise then when
you do this suit does it
that's all it talks a lot that is all
about understanding yeah you're ten
certain things that expense about it as
it please that are conducive to not lost
and the expense of things they could
used to love but only so that you can
understand the nature of them as they
are discerning the nature that is there
exactly that thing is there
yeah yeah the element of Nevada that's
what it means doesn't mean you're
already in the bottom is the possibility
of you developing the Dharma of Nevada
is possible if you know it right not
something with you it's not outside of
you five are given it's basically a
teacher didn't bring up the fire it's a
particular Dhamma of complete absence of
passion in regard to fire gates
that's why your input to jannat is that
in 30 no no no later on but he says me
talks about the conceiving I am I'm
doing this simultaneous and he says it
so much so men can even say oh this is
newborn I am I'm obtaining this Devon
and Esteban is Maya and everything oh it
must be not not the real diviner and the
Buddha says no this Ravana well this man
asserts is that which Ivana is but he
doesn't attain it as in he doesn't
actually develop it properly because he
still I am doing this so he's
appropriating so the element of Nibbana
is basically the experience of absence
of greed aversion deluge
that's what the bana is you won't
concern that one can this serve you the
more you discern it the more the context
will enjoy the more the context will
endure the less of you maintaining all
these random passions will go occur and
when those passions completely go then
one account of the context that you
start to discern it you are then in
Nibbana that's Ehrlich sotapanna understood
that's Ehrlich sotapanna understood
basically man understands the around now
he needs to develop it he needs to
maintain that context simply through not
restricted through through
non-engagement sensuality through
restraint and that's it he will have to
arrive at the complete eradication of
greed aversion delusion from the context
that has been fundamentally understood
context of inaudible unpleasurable and
thus not myself they're not my own self
it's that context has been uncovered
yeah I'll come back in a minute tip can
you create it because anything
particular can only ever be determined
by that context but not understanding
that would you mean so it you've
uncovered the context when you say
you've uncovered the context basically
you just simply uncovered that which
everything is to be yummy so everything
is determined by whether you were
whether you were aware of that or not
yeah that upon which your passion your
aversion your distraction delusion
depend is something inaccessible to your
passion to your aversion enter delusion
you fully understand that you will not
be able to maintain passion aversion
delusion in regard to that thing that's
it